Javier Carvajal-Rojas

Personal & Contact Information Callejón Jalisco S/N 36023 Col. Valenciana $+52\ 473\ 732\ 7155$

payier.carvajal@cimat.mx Guanajuato, Gto, México https://carvajalrojas.github.io/

OrcID: 0000-0002-5312-6905

Language skills: Spanish (native), English (fluent), French (basic).

RESEARCH Interests

Algebraic geometry and commutative algebra in positive and mixed characteristic. My main focus has been on Fano geometry and the geometry of Frobenius endomorphisms: Frobenius actions on Fano-type varieties and their singularities. I am generally interested in objects and concepts defined via Frobenius actions such as F-singularity theory and ordinarity.

EDUCATION

University of Utah

Ph.D. in Mathematics, August 2018

Defense date: 26.04.2018 Advisor: Prof. Karl Schwede

Dissertation: Arithmetic aspects of strong F-regularity

Universidad de Costa Rica

B.S. in Mathematics, April 2013

- Graduación de Honor
- Minor in Physics

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

CIMAT, Centro de Investigación en Matemáticas

Profesor Titular A (Assistant Professor), October 2023—

KU Leuven

Postdoctoral Fellow, September 2022—September 2023 Mentor: Prof. Wim Veys (Head of the Section of Algebra)

EPFL, The Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Lausanne

Collaborateur Scientifique (Postdoc), September 2018—September 2022 Mentor: Prof. Zsolt Patakfalvi (Chair of Algebraic Geometry)

Universidad de Costa Rica

Profesor interino (Instructor), March 2013—July 2013

PUBLICATIONS

- J. Carvajal-Rojas, A. Stäbler, J. Kollár, On the local étale fundamental group of KLT threefold singularities, Algebraic Geometry 10 (6) (2023), 694–728, doi: https://doi.org/10.14231/AG-2023-025
- 2. J. Carvajal-Rojas, A. Vilpert, Singularities of determinantal pure pairs, *Bollettino dell'Unione Matematica Italiana* (2023), doi: https://doi.org/10.1007/s40574-023-00361-z.
- 3. J. Carvajal-Rojas, A. Stäbler, Tame fundamental groups of pure pairs and Abhyankar's lemma, *Algebra & Number Theory* **17** (2023), 309–358, doi: https://doi.org/10.2140/ant.2023.17.309.
- 4. J. Carvajal-Rojas, A. Stäbler, On the behavior of *F*-signatures, splitting primes, and test modules under finite covers, *Journal of Pure and Applied Algebra* **227** (2023), 107165, doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpaa.2022.107165.
- 5. J. Carvajal-Rojas, Finite torsors over strongly F-regular singularities, Épijournal de Géometrie Algébrique 6 (2022), 1-30, doi: https://doi.org/10.46298/epiga.2022.7532
- 6. J. Carvajal-Rojas, L. Ma, T. Polstra, K. Schwede, K. Tucker, Covers of rational double points in mixed characteristic, *Journal of Singularities* **23** (2021), 127–150, doi: http://doi.org/10.5427/jsing. 2021.23h
- 7. J. Carvajal-Rojas, K. Schwede, K. Tucker, Bertini Theorems for F-signature and Hilbert-Kunz multiplicity, Mathematische Zeitschrift **299** (2021), 1131–1153, doi: https://doi.org/10.1007/s00209-021-02712-y
- 8. J. Carvajal-Rojas, D. Smolkin, The uniform symbolic topology property for diagonally *F*-regular algebras, *Journal of Algebra* **548** (2020), 25–52, doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jalgebra.2019.11.017
- 9. B. Bhatt, J. Carvajal-Rojas, P. Graf, K. Schwede, K. Tucker, Étale fundamental groups of strongly *F*-regular schemes, *International Mathematics Research Notices* **14** (2019), 4325–4339, rnx253, doi: https://doi.org/10.1093/imrn/rnx253
- 10. J. Carvajal-Rojas, K. Schwede, K. Tucker, Fundamental groups of F-regular singularities via F-signature, Annales scientifiques de l'École Normale Supérieure (4) **51** (2018), no. 4, 993–1016, doi: https://doi.org/10.24033/asens.2370
- 11. D. Campos-Salas, J. Carvajal-Rojas, M. Villarino, On the monotonicity of the correction term in Ramanujan's factorial approximation, *The Mathematical Gazette* (539) **97** (2013), 274–275, doi: https://doi.org/10.1017/S002555720000591X

SUBMITTED PAPERS & PREPRINTS

- 1. J. Carvajal-Rojas, A. Fayolle, On tame ramification and centers of F-purity, ArXiv e-prints, 2023. arXiv2308.02660.
- 2. J. Carvajal-Rojas, Zs. Patakfalvi, *Varieties with ample Frobenius-trace kernel*, ArXiv e-prints, 2021. arXiv2110.15035.
- 3. J. Carvajal-Rojas, T. Yasuda, On the behavior of stringy motives under Galois quasi-étale covers, ArXiv e-prints, 2021. arXiv2105.05214.

TEACHING ACTIVITIES

Fall	2022	Instructor, Advanced Reading Course, KU Leuven
Spring	2022	Instructor, MATH-679 Group Schemes, EPFL
Fall	2020	Teaching Assistant, MATH-510 Modern Algebraic Ge-
		ometry, EPFL
Spring	2020	Teaching Assistant, MATH-105(b) Analyse avancée II,
Fall	2018	EPFL Teaching Assistant, MATH-333 Chapitre choisi de
		géométrie: surfaces minimales, EPFL
Summer	2018	Instructor, MATH 2270 Linear Algebra, University of
Spring	2018	Utah Instructor , MATH 2270 Linear Algebra, University of
Spring	2017	Utah Teaching Assistant, MATH 1210 Calculus I, University
Fall	2016	of Utah Instructor , MATH 1210 Calculus I, University of Utah
Fall	2015	Instructor, MATH 1090 Business Algebra, University
Spring	2015	of Utah Instructor , MATH 1030 Intro. to Quantitative Reason-
		ing, University of Utah
Fall	2014	Teaching Assistant, MATH 1210 Calculus I, University
Spring	2014	of Utah Teaching Assistant, MATH 1310 Engineering Calculus II,
		University of Utah

- Fall 2013 Teaching Assistant, MATH 1310 Engineering Calculus I, University of Utah
- I Ciclo 2013 **Instructor**, MA1004-Álgebra Lineal (two sections), Universidad de Costa Rica

Master theses directed:

- 1. Maxime Matthey, F-splitting numbers of Segre pure pairs, Spring 2022, EPFL.
- 2. Anne Fayolle, Centers of F-purity and their behavior under finite covers, Spring 2022, EPFL. (Resulted in an article.)
- 3. Arnaud Vilpert, Singularities of determinantal pairs, Fall 2021, EPFL. (Resulted in an article.)

TEACHING ACTIVITIES (CONTINUED)

Reader of the master theses:

- 1. Leen Jacobs, Reidemeister Growth for Two-dimensional Crystallographic Groups, Spring 2023, KU Leuven.
- 2. Tianqi Liu, On height functions, Spring 2023, KU Leuven.

Master projects supervised:

- 1. Anne Fayolle, The test ideal and other measures of singularities in positive characteristic, Fall 2020, EPFL.
- 2. Arnaud Vilpert, The Frobenius endomorphism and singularities in positive characteristic, Fall 2020, EPFL.

Bachelor projects supervised:

- 1. Emre Ozavci, Local Cohomology, Spring 2022, EPFL.
- 2. Marco Cavaleri, Ring completions and the Cohen's structure theorem, Spring 2020, EPFL.

Summer in the Lab Program:

1. Emre Özavci, On the positivity of the Frobenius-trace kernel on toric and Hibi varieties, Summer 2022, EPFL.

Organizational Co-organizer of the Sesión Especial de Álgebra Conmu-October 2023 Activities tativa del 56 Congreso Nacional de la SMM

Talks

Coloquio CIMAT-DEMAT, CIMAT: El problema de November 2023 conexidad de variedades de Fano.

Seminario CA/GA, CIMAT: On tame ramification and October 2023 F-singularities.

Conference "Singularities", CIRM Luminy: On tame September 2023 ramification and F-singularities.

Geometry and Arithmetic Colloquium, Johannes June 2023 Gutenberg-Universität Mainz: Centers of F-purity and their behavior under finite covers.

Cibercoloquio Latinoamericano de Matemáticas, Grupos May 2023 de clases de singularidades F-regulares. Recording

Algebraic and Arithmetic Geometry Seminar, Universität Bielefeld: Centers of F-purity and their behavior under finite covers.

Number Theory and Algebraic Geometry Seminar, KU January 2023 Leuven: Singularities of determinantal pairs. Talks (continued)

Commutative Algebra Seminar, Purdue University: Cen- November 2022 ters of F-purity and finite extensions.

55 Congreso Nacional de la SMM, Universidad de October 2022 Guadalajara: $Centros\ de\ F$ -pureza $y\ extensiones\ finitas$. Recording

Commutative Algebra Seminar, University of Michigan: April 2022 F-singularities of determinantal pairs.

Algebraic Geometry Seminar, Princeton University: Varieties with ample Frobenius-trace kernel: in the search of a Frobenius-theoretic characterization of projective spaces. Recording

11-th Swiss-French workshop in Algebraic Geometry, January 2022 Charmey Switzerland: Varieties with ample Frobenius-trace kernel: in the search of a Frobenius-theoretic characterization of projective spaces.

Groups, Arithmetic & Algebraic Geometry Seminar, May 2021 EPFL: On the behavior of stringy motives under Galois quasi-étale covers.

Online Algebraic Geometry Seminar, Yale University: May 2020 On the fundamental group of KLT threefold singularities in positive characteristic.

Algebra and Representation Theory Seminar (ARTS), May 2020 University of Oklahoma: Fundamental groups of KLT singularities.

Conference "Singularities and Arithmetics," Tohoku Uni- February 2020 versity: Étale fundamental groups of rational KLT three-fold singularities in positive characteristic.

FACARD 2019 Workshop, Institut de Matemàtica Universitat de Barcelona: Tame fundamental groups of purely F-regular pairs.

SFB/TRR45 Kolloquium, Johannes Gutenberg- December 2018 Universität Mainz: The USTP property and diagonal F-regularity.

Intercity BeNeFri Seminar, Université de Neuchâtel: *The* November 2018 *USTP property and diagonal F-regularity*.

Talks (continued)

Basel-Dijon-EPFL Joint Seminar, Institut de October 2018 Mathématiques de Bourgogne-Dijon: Towards a purity-for-torsors theorem for F-regular singularities.

Groups, Arithmetic & Algebraic Geometry Seminar, October 2018 EPFL: Arithmetic aspects of strong F-regularity.

Grupo de Trabajo en Geometría y Topología, Universidad de Costa Rica: Aspectos aritméticos de la Frequiaridad fuerte.

Commutative Algebra Seminar, University of Michigan: October 2017 Finite torsors over strongly F-regular singularities.

Algebra Seminar, Universität Osnabrück: Finite torsors October 2017 over strongly F-regular singularities.

SFB/TRR45 Colloquium, Johannes Gutenberg- September 2017 Universität Mainz: Finite torsors over strongly F-regular singularities.

FRAGMENT Seminar, Colorado State University: Fun- April 2017 damental groups of F-regular schemes and singularities.

Algebraic Geometry Seminar, University of Illinois at March 2017 Chicago: Fundamental groups of F-regular schemes and singularities.

Commutative Algebra Seminar, University of Utah: Fun-September 2016 damental groups of strongly F-regular singularities via F-signature.

Departmental Colloquium, Universidad de Costa Rica: June 2016 F-singularidades y grupos fundamentales locales.

Conference Posters

- 1. Finite torsors over strongly F-regular singularities (PDF), presented at:
 - Western Algebraic Geometry Symposium, University of California at Los Angeles, October 2017.
 - Local Cohomology in Commutative Algebra and Algebraic Geometry Conference in honor of Gennady Lyubeznik's 60th birthday, University of Minnesota, August 2017.

- 2. Fundamental groups of strongly F-regular singularities via F-signature (PDF), presented at:
 - Western Algebraic Geometry Symposium, Colorado State University, October 2016.
 - KUMUNU Conference, University of Kansas, October 2016.
 - Summer School and Conference in Higher Dimensional Algebraic Geometry, University of Utah, July 2016.
 - Commutative Algebra Conference in honor of Craig Huneke's 65th birthday, University of Michigan, July 2016.

Refereeing Service

Proceedings of the 2015 AMS Summer Institute, Nagoya Mathematical Journal, IMRN, Astérisque, Bulletin of the Belgian Mathematical Society, Bulletin of the London Mathematical Society, EPIGA.

Prizes and fellowships

August	2012	Diploma de Excelencia Académica—awarded to the stu-
		dent with the best grades in the section.
March	2012	Beca de excelencia académica—awarded to students with

March 2012 Beca de excelencia académica—awarded to students with an average above 9/10, waives tuition for the academic year.

August 2011 Diploma de Excelencia Académica March 2011 Beca de excelencia académica March 2010 Beca de excelencia académica March 2009 Beca de excelencia académica